In the last segment in this module, I
wanna show you a general attack that
在本单元最后一节里
affects many implementations of Mac
algorithms. And there's a nice lesson to
我来展示一个影响许多MAC算法实现的通用攻击
be learned from an attack like this. So
let's look at a particular implementation
从这个攻击中能学到很多，那么我们来看一个具体的HMAC验证的实现
of HMAC verification. This happens to be
an implementation from the Keyczar library,
这正好是Keyczar库的实现，使用Python编写
that happens to be written in Python. So
here's the code that's used to verify a
这个代码用来验证HMAC生成的标签
tag generated by HMAC. This code is
actually simplified. I just wanted to
代码实际是被简化了
kinda simplify it as much as I can to get
the point across. So basically, what the
我想使之尽可能简单而保留核心要点
inputs are, the key, the message, and the
tag bytes. The way we verify it is, we
输入的是密钥，消息，和标签字节
re-compute the HMAC on the message and
then we compare say the resulting sixteen
验证的方法是重新计算消息HMAC得到16个字节
bytes. To the actual given signature
bites. So this looks perfectly fine.
与给出的签名字节相比较。这看上去没有问题
In fact, anyone might implement it like this.
And, in fact, many people have implemented
任何人都有可能这么实现，事实上许多人的确就是这样实现的
it like this. The problem is, that if you
look at how the comparison is done, the
问题在于，如果你去观察比较的方式的话
comparison, as you might expect, is done
byte by byte. There's a loop inside of the
正如你所想，比较是逐字节比较的
Python interpreter that loops over all
sixteen bytes. And it so happens that the
Python的解释器内部有一个循环遍历所有16个字节
first time it finds an inequality, the
loop terminates and says the strings are
只要发现不同就立刻终止循环，表示字符串不相同
not equal. And the fact that the
comparator exits when the first inequality
比较器存在，直到找到第一个不同
is found introduces a significant timing
attack on this library. So let me show you
这就能对这个库进行时间攻击
how one might attack it. So imagine you're
the attacker, and you have the message m,
让我们来看是如何攻击的。假设你是攻击者，拥有消息m
for which you want to obtain a valid tag.
Now, your goal is to attack a server that
你想得到对应有效的标签，你的目标是攻击一个拥有HMAC密钥的服务器
has an HMAC secret key stored in it. And
the server exposes an interface that
服务器接收一对消息和MAC
basically takes message MAC pairs. Checks
that the MAC is valid, if the MAC is valid
检查MAC是否有效，如果有效就对消息做某些处理
it does something with the message. And if
the MAC is not valid, it says reject.
如果无效就拒绝
Okay, so it's back to the originator or
the message rejects. So now this attacker
回到初始或者拒绝
has an opportunity to basically submit
lots of message it appears and see if it
因此攻击者可以提交大量消息和MAC对
can deduce the tags of the particular
message for which it once attacked. Here's
观察能否推测出给定消息的标签
how we might use the broken implementation
from the previous slide to do just that.
下面我们来利用前面讲到的糟糕的实现
So what the attacker is gonna do is to
submit many message tag queries, where the
攻击者要做的就是提交许多消息标签询问，每次的消息都相同
message is always the same. But with a
tag, he's gonna experiment with lots and
而用很多很多不同的标签
lots and lots of different tags. So in the
first query, what he's gonna do is just
所以在第一次询问中
submit a random tag along with the target
message. And he's gonna measure how long
只需用一个随机的标签和特定消息，然后测出服务器给出回应的时间
the server took to respond. The next query
that he's gonna submit, is he's gonna try
下一次提交的询问，他就要尝试标签的首字节的所有可能性
all possible first bytes for the tags. Let
me explain what I mean by that. So the
我来解释一下
remaining bytes of the tags that he
submits are just arbitrary, doesn't really
标签剩下的字节都是任意的，无关紧要的
matter what they are. But for the first
bite, what he'll do is he'll submit a tag
但对于首字节，他会提交一个首字节为0的标签
starting with a byte zero. And then he's
gonna see whether the server took a little
然后观察服务器是不是比之前比较的时间长
bit longer to verify the tag than before.
If the server took exactly the same amount
如果服务器比较的时间和第一步的时间相同的话
of time to verify the tag as in step one,
then he's gonna try again, this time with
然后他用首字节为1的标签再试一次
bytes at one. If still the server
responded very quickly, he's going to try
如果服务器回应仍然很快的话
with byte sets of two. If the server
responded quickly then he's going to try
他就用首字节为2的标签再试。如果服务器回应仍然很快的话
with byte sets of three, and so on until
finally, let's say, when the byte sets of
他就用首字节为3标签再试
three the server takes a little bit longer
to respond. What that means is actually
直到最后首字节为3时，服务器回应的时间比以前长了一点
when it did the comparison between the
correct MAC and the MAC submitted by the
这说明在正确的MAC和攻击者提交的MAC进行比较时
attacker. The two matched on this byte,
and the rejection happened on the second
在这个字节上是匹配的，在第二个字节上被拒绝了
bytes. Aha. So now the attacker knows that
the first bite of the tag is set to three
因此攻击者知道了标签的第一个字节是3
and now he can mount exactly the same
attack on the second bite. So here. It's
现在他可以在第二个字节上重复相同的攻击
going to submit the tag. And the second,
back here. Here This should go here. So
it's gonna submit a tag when the second
byte is set to zero. And it's gonna
提交第二字节是0的标签
measure whether this took a little bit
longer than in step two. If not, he's
然后测量时间是不是比第二步的时间长
gonna change this to be set to one, and
he's gonna measure if the server's
如果不是，就把这个字节改成1
response time is a little longer than
before. Eventually, let's say when he sets
然后测量时间是不是比之前长
this to, I don't know. When the byte is
set to, to 53, say, all of a sudden, the
最后，当这个字节为...53时
server takes a little bit longer to
respond. Which means that now, the
时间比之前长
comparator matched on the first two bytes.
And now the attacker learned that the
说明前两个字节都匹配了
first two bytes of the Mac are three and
53. And now he can move on and do the
攻击者知道MAC的前两个字节为3和53
exact same thing on the third byte and
then on the fourth byte and so on and so
然后他对第三字节做同样的事，然后是第四个
forth. Until finally, the server says,
yes, I accept. You actually gave me the
直到最后服务器说，好我接受了，你给出了正确的MAC
right Mac. And then we'll go ahead and act
on this bogus message. That, attack our
然后我们就能使用这个伪造的消息了
supply. So this is a beautiful example of
how a timing attack can reveal the value
所以这是一个好例子
of a MAC, the correct value of the MAC.
Kind of byte by byte, until eventually,
用时间攻击逐字节获得正确的MAC字节
the attacker obtains all the correct bytes
of the tag, and then he's able to fool the
直到最后得到标签的所有正确字节
server into accepting this message tag
pair. The reason I like this example is
然后他就能欺骗服务器，使之接受消息标签对
this is a perfectly reasonable way of
implementing a MAC verification routine.
我喜欢这个例子的原因是它是实现MAC验证程序的一个完全合理的方式
And yet, if you right it this way, it will
be completely broken. So what do we do? So
然而，如果你用这种方式纠正它，它会被彻底地攻破。那么我们该怎么做呢？
let me show you two defenses, the first
defense, I'll write it in again in python
让我来给你展示两种防御方式，第一种防御，我会用程序按照如下的方式
is, is as follows. In fact the Keyczar
library exactly implemented this defense.
再把它写一遍。事实上Keyczar库恰好执行了这种防御
This code is actually taken out of the
updated version of the library. The first
这个代码实际上被用于库的更新方案
thing we do is we test if the signature
bytes submitted by the attacker are of the
我们要做的第一件事是我们要测试攻击者使用的签名字节是否是正确的长度
correct length, say for HMAC this would
be say, you know 96 bits or 128 bits, and
HMAC这将是说，你知道96比特或者128比特，
if not we reject that as an invalid MAC.
But now, if the signature bytes really do
如果不是我们拒绝它作为一个无效的MAC。但是现在，如果签名字节确实有正确的长度
have the correct length, what we do is
implement our own comparator. And it
那么我们要做的就是完成我们自己的比较
always takes the same amount of time to
compare the two strings. So in particular,
比较两个字符串总是需要同等量的时间。所以特别地，
this uses the zip function in Python,
which will, essentially, if you are giving
这个用邮编函数在程序中，将本质上，如果你给它两个16字节的字符串
it two sixteen byte strings. It will
create sixteen pairs. Of bytes. So it'll
两个16字节的字符串。它会创造出16对字节。
just create a, a list of sixteen elements,
where each element is a pair of bytes. One
所以它会创造出一系列16要素，每个要素都是一对字节。
taken from the left and one taken from the
right. And then you loop, you know, you
一个取自左边一个取自右边。然后你循环你会知道
loop through this list of pairs. You
compute the XOR of the first pair, and the
你会依次取遍这一系列对。你计算一下第一对的异或，再将结果取或
OR into the result. Then you
compute the XOR of the second pair, and
然后计算第二对的异或，再对结果取或。
you OR that into the result. And
you note that, if at any point in this
你会注意到，如果在这个循环中的任一点上，
loop, two bytes happen to be not equal,
then the XOR will evaluate to something
两个字节恰好不是相等的，然后异或会评估那些非零的。
that's non zero. And therefore, when we
OR'ed it into the result. The result
因此，当我们再对它取或后得到结果。
will also be counting on zero, and then
we'll return false, at the end of the
这结果也会算到零，我们会返回一个错误在比较以后。
comparison. So the point here is that now
the comparator always takes the same
所以关键就是现在比较者总会用同等量的时间
amount of time. Even if it finds
difference in byte number three, it will
即使它发现第三个字节不同，
continue running down the both strings
until the very end. And only then will it
它会继续惰转在两个字符串直到结尾。直到它返回结果。
return the results. So now the timing
attack supposedly is impossible. However,
所以现在计时攻击被认为是不可能的。
this can be quite problematic, because
compilers tried to be too helpful here. So
然而，这可能是相当有问题的，因为编译器试图在这里起很大作用。
an optimized compiler might look at this
code and say, hey, wait a minute. I can
所以一个优化的编译器可能会看这个代码并说,嘿,等一下
actually improve this code by making the
four loop end. As soon as an incompatible
我能通过使四个循环结束来改善这个代码。
set of bytes is discovered. And so, an
optimizing compiler could be your, kind
一旦发现不兼容的字节，并且，一个优化的编译器可能是你，有时，
of, Achilles heel when it comes to making
programs always take the same amount of
薄弱的环节当它总是花同样的时间来走程序的时候
time. And so a different defense, which is
not as widely implemented, is to try and
所以不同的防御,没被广泛实施的,
hide from the adversary, what strings are
actually being compared. So let me show
试图躲避对手,字符串实际上是被比较的。
you what I mean by that. So again, here we
have our verification algorithm. So it
让我来向你展示我所说的意思。再来一次，在这里我们有我们的验证算法。
takes as inputs, a key, a message, and a
candidate's MAC from the adversary. And
所以它需要作为输入,一个键,一个消息,一个来自敌手的候选人的MAC。
then, the way we do the comparison is we
first of all, compute the correct MAC on
然后，我们做比较是我们首先,计算正确的MAC上的消息。
the message. But then instead of directly
comparing the MAC and the signature
但随后而不是直接比较MAC和签名字节的敌手,我们要做的是我们要散列一次
bytes adversary, what we're gonna do
is we're gonna hash one more time. So we
我们要做的是我们要哈希一次。
compute a hash here of the MAC. We compute
a hash of the signature bytes. Of course,
所以我们这里计算MAC的哈希值。我们计算签名字节的哈希值。当然，
if these two happen to be the same, then
the resulting HMACs will also be the
如果这两个恰好是相同的，然后HMACs的结果也将会是相同的，
same, so the comparison will actually
succeed. But the point is now, if sig
所以比较就会成功。但是关键是现在，如果签名的字节
bytes happen to equal MAC on the first
byte, but not on the remaining bytes.
恰好和MAC的相同在一个字节中，但在剩余的字节里不同。
Then, when we do this additional hash
layer, it's likely that the two resulting
当我们做这些额外的散列层,很有可能这两个结果
values are completely different. And as a
result, the byte by byte comparator will
是完全不同的。因此,字节的字节比较器只会在第一次迭代输出。
just output on the first iteration. The
point here is that the adversary doesn't
只会在第一次迭代输出。这里的关键是敌手不确切地知道
actually know what strings are being
compared. And as a result, he can't
什么字符串正在被比较。因此，
mount a timing attack that we
discussed earlier. Okay, so this is
他不能装载一个之前我们讨论过的计时攻击。好的，
another defense. At least now, you're not
at the mercy of an optimizing compiler.
所以这就是另一个防御。至少现在，你不会在被一个优化的编译器摆布了。
The main lesson from all of this is that
you realize that people who even are
所有这一切的主要内容是,你意识到那些已经在实施密文库中成为专家的人
experts at implementing cryptolibraries,
get this stuff wrong. And the right code
误会了这些东西。正确的代码
that words perfectly fine and yet is
completely vulnerable to a timing attack
表达地非常完美并且是完全易遭受计时攻击的
that completely undo all security of the
system. So the lesson here is of course
这种攻击能完全地破坏系统的所有安全。所以这里要学到的当然是
you should not be inventing your own
crypto but you shouldn't even be
你不应该发明自己的密码,你甚至不应该实现自己的密码,
implementing your own crypto because most
likely it'll be vulnerable to the side
因为很有可能它容易受到侧信道攻击。
channel attacks. Just use a standard
library like OpenSSL. Keyczar is actually a
只是用一个标准的库像OpenSSL.Keyczar实际上是
fine library to use that would reduce the
chances that you're vulnerable to these
一个很好地库，用它会减少你遭受这些类型的攻击的机会。
types of attacks.